Jacob C. Solovay Papers, 1947-1988
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Jacob C. Solovay Papers, 1947-1988
MS 532
Solovay, Jacob C.
The collection of Jacob C. Solovay contains unpublished and published poetry; two unpublished manuscripts; and personal correspondence pertaining to Mr. Solovay’s published material.
1.25 linear ft.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Biographical Note
Jacob “Jack” C. Solovay (1909-1986) was a high school English teacher and journalism adviser at Fort Hamilton High School in Brooklyn, New York. In 1964, he was the Columbia Scholastic Press’s Gold Key Recipient as recognition for his teaching excellence and advising in journalism. After developing heart health issues, Mr. Solovay and his wife Ethel retired to Tucson. Meanwhile, Mr. Solovay published two collections of poetry, Headspins of a Pedagog (1959) and Sherlock Holmes: Two Sonnet Sequences (1969). Additionally, some 200 separate poems were reproduced in many publications ranging from the English Review to the New York Times. His publications span between the years 1947-1970. His poetry addressed light and serious tones, education, literature, nature, and philosophy.
Upon his passing, Mr. Solovay’s family and friends bestowed memorial donations of his published titles to the University of Arizona Poetry Center as well as a combined collection of his published titles and a selection of his favorite works of literature to the Wilmot Branch of the Pima County Public Library in 1988.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 3 series.
Series I:Poetry 1947-1970
Series II:Manuscripts Undated
Series III:Correspondence 1958-1988
Scope and Content Note
This collection mainly consists of Jacob C. Solovay’s poetry and manuscripts. There is not much information on Solovay’s personal life in this collection. The poetry series consists of two parts, unpublished and published poetry. The unpublished poetry is divided into light and serious volumes. The light unpublished poetry consists of a solitary volume and folder containing his wife’s favorite unpublished works. The unpublished serious poetry is divided into two volumes, A-M and N-Z. The published poetry is self-bound and loose-leaf with a listing of corresponding publications. The second series of the collection also includes two unpublished manuscripts written in mixed points of view. One manuscript is titled, Peppy, the Story of a House Finch which includes the point of view of a house finch and that of Mr. Jess. The second manuscript is titled, Mama is a Hummingbird, which is told from the point of view a black chin hummingbird and that of Mr. Jess, a shared character in both manuscripts. The third series is correspondence which contains Christmas cards imprinted with his poetry. There are also letters regarding Mr. Solovay’s poetry and donations to the Wilmot Branch of the Pima County Public Library.
Access Terms
Education-- Teachers-- High School--Literature.
Nature--Fiction
Tucson--Arizona--United States.
Poetry—Light Verse
Verses (Poetry)
Container List
- Series I: Poetry, 1947-1970
  Contains unpublished light and serious verse and published verse.
  - Unpublished Light Verse, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Unpublished Serious Verse A-M, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Unpublished Serious Verse N-Z, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The English Review, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Published Poems: Volume 1, 1947-1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Published Poems: Volume 2, 1957-1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series II: Manuscripts, Undated
  This series contains Solovay’s unpublished manuscripts.
  - Peppy, the Story of a House Finch, Contains A Table of Contents, Chapter synopses, Author’s Note, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Mama is a Hummingbird: Original Manuscript, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Peppy, the Story of a House Finch, Chapter 5: Chatterboxes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series III: Personal Correspondence, 1958-1988
  Solovay’s correspondence contains a listing of publications, Christmas card poems, and letters of awards.
  - Correspondence, 1958-1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)